hello and welcome it's January 26 2023
we're here in active inference model
stream number 8.1
today we're appreciative to have Thomas
ringstrom
who will be presenting on reward is not
necessary a compositional theory of
self-preserving Agents with empowerment
gain maximization there will be a
presentation followed by a discussion so
Thomas thank you for joining really
looking forward to this off to you
yeah thank you very much it's really
nice to be here and talk to this uh to
this group
um I'm uh a computer science PhD student
at the University of Minnesota uh my my
interests are in sort of what you know
what are the composition what are the uh
sort of computational properties that we
would need to have
uh agents which
um flexibly plan in sort of high
dimensional you know product spaces of
variables
um and also how do we get agents to
perform complex tasks uh in an
intrinsically motivated way especially
in in high dimensional product spaces
um so this uh this presentation is going
to argue that
um reward uh and I know I'm talking to a
sort of active inference crowd um
but uh some of the same points apply to
active inference perhaps too but I this
this presentation is is mostly about how
there there's going to be some major
problems I think uh using reward
maximization objectives and by moving to
sort of reward free objective functions
we can get really nice
um factorizations that help us plan so
let's just start off with a sort of
simple picture a simplified picture of
an organism so we have a honey badger
here and
um
so this honey badger has
internal States it gets hungry and it
gets thirsty and there's also an
external World
um that the agent lives in
and you know in order to sort of modify
internal State spaces the the agent
might have to
perform some complex tasks
um it might have to get several items uh
in order to you know eat eat an apple or
things like that so you could you could
see that maybe maybe
um some symbolic State space sort of
mediates the connection between things
you do in the world and Transformations
that you make on some internal State
space and of course real you know Real
Worlds
um organisms and humans are live in a
high dimensional world so you could
imagine that there's an encoder and a
decoder
and really you know there's a sort of
high dimensional uh physiological or
interceptive
um domain that that is these sort of Y
tilde with the dot
um for y tilde I should say and Z tell
them and then there's you know High
dimensional worlds you could just say
that the that's X tilde
and really you just need to sort of uh
map these down to some discrete State
space in which uh these domains can uh
interact
so
yeah here here's like a simple encoder
and decoder and
and so if if an agent
has a kind of simple ontology like this
you can imagine that it's sort of
generatively entrained to the world uh
that it lives in
uh which is a notion that's probably
um pretty familiar to sort of active
inference uh people
um so you know you have some encoder of
these high dimensional States and then
you have some uh operator PS which is in
the middle of the head here and that
just sort of advances the latent States
and then you decode and you'll get a
sort of expectations of of the high
dimensional world that the the agent
lives in
and so
the problem is is that you can't really
represent explicitly these latent space
transition operators that would dictate
you know the Dynamics of of all these
variables you can't represent it as an
explicit object because the more State
spaces that you keep track of in the
world uh the larger this uh object PS
becomes so
in order to handle this you'd have to
represent it in a sort of factorized
form so you just would represent its
factors you wouldn't explicitly sort of
enumerate all of the state Vector
transitions under under this transition
operator
and so
what we really need to think about is
you know what are the sort of model
based
or the sort of bellman principles for
decomposing hierarchical State spaces
um so that we can create the right
representations that help us plan in a
flexible way in a sort of time to time
varying time dependent uh world of lots
of lots of variables so this just means
um you know what is a sort of objective
function L telegraphic L applied to PS
or its factorization that would give us
um that would give us some factors here
uh Ada and and these omegas that could
help us plan
and also
how you know given the fact that you
know the state space the effective
product space that we're working at is
so large and there's many possible State
vectors that describe possible states of
the world how do you know what to do I
mean if you're an RL theorist you would
have to say well there exists some kind
of reward function that tells you you
know this state of the world is is worth
this much reward in this state of the
world is worth this much reward but it's
not really clear how you should Define
reward functions on huge product spaces
so I'll address this a question from uh
sort of reward free perspective and the
just to give you a hint of what it's
going to be like what I'm going to argue
is that what we really need are agents
that have a kind of structured core
ontology that it needs to maintain that
is coupled State spaces that really
depend on each other
in which the policies that you use
maintain the sort of internal Integrity
or controllability of the agent
um
so
and that's where empowerment will
eventually come in so I'll talk about
empowerment a little too that's the
controllability metric
so
um here I'm just saying what's a nice
policy or what's an objective function f
that takes in some intrinsic motivation
function which is this fancy V here
along with a nice factorization that
that allows you to plan in the world
okay so just to recap things that I
already said
um we're in a product space of uh state
of variables we have internal and
external State spaces
um you know hunger and hydration State
spaces can be dynamic as you do things
in the world you get hungrier
um so how do we plan how do we know what
a good goal is and what I'm going to
argue is that we should compute a
specific representation called estate
time feasibility function
which is going to be an abstraction uh
that's going to map us from initial
State times to final State times and
this will have some really nice
properties that allow us to sort of
reason in this High dimensional uh State
space and I'm going to talk about this
from a just a dynamic programming uh
point of view there's there isn't going
to be any learning
okay so let's just talk about transition
operator composition because I said well
we have this large product space State
variables and it'd be nice if we just
represent it as a factorization so what
does that mean
um
so imagine that you have PX which is
like a base State space to move around
the world and you have some internal
State space or secondary State space p y
and these are linked by some function f
so here's your base State space and uh
here's the honey badger in the state
space
and here's the secondary State space
which is just like a you know your
internal hunger space
um and so F what f is going to be is
called an availability function and an
availability function is going to say oh
this you know this honey badger is in
state x a t and at time T and given that
it's there
um what's the probability that this goal
is available from this State time State
action time and so this goal is formally
going to be an action on the higher
level State space so for instance these
green lines on the uh high-level State
space are going to map you to you know
the most
satiated uh state where you're not
hungry anymore at all and then these
black lines on the on the internal State
space are just going to decrement you
you know one States if you're if you're
not at the tree so you eat apples at the
tree and that's going to map you to the
top and all other states without a tree
you're going to get hungrier over time
okay so if we wanted to write a product
space operator uh you know PDS you know
y Prime X Prime
uh we can just represent this as a
composition where Lambda p is our
composition operator and it's just going
to be defined as the product of uh your
two State spaces with f linking them and
then we sum over G so we're getting rid
of the goal variable and so we can
represent the uh the product space this
way and we can also just call the
product space we can say that s bold s
here is just the state Vector for you
know Y X or if we have more variables
that can be incorporated into bold s
Okay so
what if we have more features of the
world we can drink water or we can get
warm at the house
um well we will need to have a a bigger
composition so we can just create an
operator called we'll just call PR or
bold R is just a state factor of w y and
c and W Y and Z correspond to the
hydration uh the the hunger and the
temperature space
and so this is just a product of the
individual ones uh individual operators
and so this influence graph is
connecting PX to uh PW p y and TZ
through F and so we can just Define the
product space operator as a composition
this way
and if we do that you know you start to
realize well this is nice because the
effect of State space you know
exponentiates essentially you know as
you add on more State spaces that you
can control
and so this influence graph is just
showing you know you know what is the
sort of ontology of the agent what is
what what constitutes it uh as its
internal and external coupling
and you could imagine that it gets more
complicated for instance that if you hit
you know w0 or y y zero or whatever that
you you these skull and crossbones
indicates that you die so you can
imagine being in a state has a
bi-directional influence so Zeta here is
um is conditioning the possible Dynamics
PX can produce so you could imagine that
you know once you're in one of those
sort of defective bad states that it
kills you and you can't move around so
you can imagine you know sort of more
complicated uh structures like this
which essentially mean that you have to
go out in the world and do things in
order to keep the system alive uh so you
don't want to hit W you know w w naught
or Z naught
um and you can imagine this gets even
more complicated you could compose sort
of larger structures where P Sigma is
going to be some logical State space
that keeps track of you know multiple
conditional events that need to occur to
for say you know say eat eaten apple or
something like that
um
so representing it in this form is is
very nice we just represent the factors
and the the links between the state
spaces and that's a sort of a sort of
memory efficient way of representing the
space
okay so if we have a homeostatic task
um I'll eventually get to the the sort
of bellman equations in the model based
form formulas but first i'm just going
to sort of uh build up an intuition in
the form of an example about how these
State time feasibility functions are
going to work the the state times
usability function being the the
representation that I'm arguing for in
in this talk
so if we have a hiker
um and it can go into the world and
drink and eat and get warm
uh with these goal variables well there
there's also
um this goal variable G Epsilon which is
going to uh decrement by by one uh by
one state
then as the uh as the hiker moves around
you can
you could represent this as a function
so imagine that the hiker starts at xg1
that's the house
and TS which is the start time and if
the hiker follows a policy Pi 2. so
imagine that you have a policy that is a
goal like a gold condition policy Pi G2
that's going to take you to xg2
okay so it's a policy it's like a
shortest path policy or whatever
um then that means that there's going to
be some final State time xg2 TF
uh that you achieve this goal g-drink
which remember is is an action on the
higher level space
so what this would look like is that you
decrement two rights because that takes
two time steps to get to the leg and
then once you get to the lake you take
the state action that's going to drink
and it's going to bring you up so
there's there's three total steps in
this uh process of uh inducing the drink
goal variable and then the step after
drinking
which would look like this
and then you can imagine well the other
state spaces are are not involved and so
they will all decrement three because
there's three time steps
and so one way to represent this is is
to realize that uh if all of these goal
variable sort of goal variables on the
way to the um to the lake are sort of
the null goal variables meaning that the
agent isn't affecting some other state
space
then you can Define that as a Markov
chain so if you set you know all of the
goals to be uh the Epsilon goal the null
goal
then this py Epsilon is going to be
um a Markov chain Matrix and so that
means that the time difference
um
encoded in the state time feasibility
function the TF minus TS is going to be
the power that you can take this Markov
chain to in order to forward evolve the
uh this the internal State spaces all
the other internal State spaces so you
can define a an operator that does this
in one step called Omega Y which is just
going to take some initial States so
this Green Dot or this Red Dot
[Music]
um
and it's going to take the time
difference so this is going to be 2 to
get from the house to the lake it's two
time steps and so these uh gray arcs are
just a an initial to final state map
under this policy
and so
what this looks like this is sort of
looks sort of complicated but you can
build a jump operator that jumps you
from your initial High dimensional state
for instance y x t
and we're just considering why for now I
don't have the other state spaces uh w
and z in here but uh this Ada over here
is is mapping you on the X space the
Omega Y is mapping you forward to in in
the uh
in the y space and then the py and the p
x are just evolving by one step
um to update after you hit the goal so
after you hit the goal you have to
update by one step so uh p y and PS do
that for both state spaces and then of
course
you can do this for all the state spaces
so a jump operator for all of the
internal State spaces are
where R is you know remembers the vector
of all your internal States w y and z
then this is similarly defined where
umega
Omega R is just the product of all of
these other omegas so we defined Omega y
up here but you can just Define this for
all of your other state spaces
so
now that we've done that we can continue
our journey by going to the tree
and so that's two steps away so all of
the other things decrement two and then
an additional one
and then if we go back to the house
that's four times steps away plus the
the additional time step of uh entering
the housing and getting warm
okay
so
here is another route you could take
uh where the uh agent the hiker goes to
the tree to eat and then the hiker goes
to the lake to drink
and then goes back to the house to get
warm and so this is this JS is a huge
it's important to keep in mind that JS
is a huge operator and we cannot
uh explicitly form it in memory uh
because it's unless we have you know a
lot of memory on our computer
um but having this factorization allows
us to chain policies together and evolve
a high dimensional State vector in these
jumps so we're we're jumping a state
Vector around in this object-oriented
fashion where each state Vector is
updated once you get to some key object
of Interest such as the tree with the
the apple or the lake with the water
so um also in this uh example you can
see that it the the agent went from the
lake to the house and
um technically if Z it it occupies the
lowest State Z zero and so technically
it should die uh at least skull and
crossbones on the map but we let it
finish uh his journey and we haven't
talked about this sort of bi-directional
coupling yet but we'll we'll do that in
the next slide to
um to make that concrete
all right
so
if we have these defective States we can
define mode parameters e plus and E
minus which
um are just going to be variables that
condition our Dynamics and we can have a
mode function that takes any Vector r
uh and so an R is any Vector of blue
green and red squares in the space and
we can map it to a mode parameter so we
can Define Zeta
to map to the good mode the the normal
healthy mode
um if it's not occupying any of the
defective States but if one one or more
um you know defective states are
occupied then we can map it to e minus
and so that means if we have some you
know low level transition operator
that's indexed by E that means we can
split it into a normal Dynamics
p e plus and a defective Dynamics p e
minus and you just know notice that the
defective Dynamics is the sort of
identity operation it just sort of
arrests your Dynamics in the space so
you can't move around but the normal
Dynamics is just normal grid world uh
movement
okay and so what we can do is we can
compute a set of individual feasibility
functions for each object of interest in
the map so in in the previous example we
had you know two trees two lakes and a
house so it would have five state-time
feasibility functions
and then this Ada hat is an aggregate
function of of all of these uh functions
where the pi is indexing the
corresponding Pi for that function
of anyone can ask questions by the way
if they have any questions
all right
all right so
the full Dynamics is going to be just
defined like we defined it before where
we uh we have uh these two State spaces
the base State space coupled to the
internal State space through F but then
we have this Zeta uh R here on the
conditioning side and so this is a sort
of uh a a an operator that you sort of
have to
uh you have to achieve goals in order to
keep yourself out of uh these sort of
absorbing defective States
and this is and I showed this um
influence diagram before but this
influence diagram uh is capturing uh
this coupling
Okay so
um
many of you will probably be familiar
with the standard Bellman equations
um
where which are you know formalized this
way where you have some reward function
plus some discounted expectation of your
future value and so the value function
in a sort of standard Bellman equation
says how much reward am I going to get
if I act
um here optimally
um over an infinite Horizon
and so the reward function is that's
often thought to be a task it has that
sort of semantics in in RL land
um
and then the optimal policy is just
going to return the action uh that
corresponds to the best action that
maximizes your value your long run sum
of rewards that you're going to get
so this is a a recursive equation and
but in this
uh my my thesis is is is that we need to
rethink the sort of model-based bellman
uh formalizations in order to compute
these nice factorizations that move us
around High dimensional space like we've
been talking about on the previous
slides
so we're going to formalize some new
development equations called operator
development equations
and these are going to be
uh non-stationary development equations
or they're going to be functions of time
so instead of having a value function
that says you know what's the
accumulated reward that I get I'm going
to have a cumulative feasibility
function Kappa
and this is going to represent what is
the cumulative probability that I
achieve a particular goal where a goal
remember is an action on a higher level
space
so this has a very similar form to the
infinite Horizon development equation
that I just showed but you'll notice
that we have this availability function
here for a specific goal so this is a
single goal G that we're picking out so
say the uh the Eden Apple goal or the
drink the water goal we're just choosing
one
and so f is
um returning the availability of G from
any given State and time and action
and then so it either the agent achieves
a goal now which is what this equation
is saying or which is the plus the agent
does not achieve the goal so one minus
the probability of achieving the goal is
the probability that you you don't
achieve the goal
times the expectation that you achieve
it in the future so it has this similar
recursive structure that the infinite
Horizon development equation has
okay so then we have the policy and this
policy equation is a little different
from the last one because you can
imagine that you can maximize the
cumulative that you achieve a goal but
you you sort of do it at the last second
you have a lot of you have maximized
certainty that you can get to the store
right before it closes so you have you
know you know 100 that you can achieve
the goal of getting an item from the
store you know five minutes before it
closes well it might be if the store is
open for some you know period of time
that
um
essentially you might want to get it as
soon as possible so what this equation
is saying is that we're going to
pick the action
which maximizes the cumulative but from
that set of equivalent actions that
maximize the cumulative which is a star
so we're collecting the actions that
maximize the cumulative and we're going
to pick the one that minimizes the time
so this is a sort of conditional
optimization that says you know subject
to the fact that we want to maximize the
cumulative we want to get there as fast
as we can
um and so normally there's just you know
with the infinite Horizon development
equation there's the value function in
the policy here we have a third
um uh function which is the state time
feasibility function which I've been
talking about
and the state time feasibility function
says given that I start at x and t
what's the probability that I achieve a
goal G
at a particular State final State and
time XF and TF
and so
um you can compute this via dynamic
programming as you're Computing these
other functions
and
um there's a relationship between the
cumulative feasibility and the state
time feasibility which is that if you
you can sum up the individual spinal
States and times in that uh from your
state time feasibility and that is the
cumulative
so the cumulative feasibility it's just
summing over the individual
probabilities of a of a given State
final State time
and the nice property is that when you
move when you use these operator Bellman
equations on hierarchical state spaces
such as the product space
um of the agent's core ontology
um it has a nice decomposition property
which is that if you're just solving to
go to a particular point in the world
then you can actually you compute Ada
separately from the high level space so
you just solve for for Ada the state
time feasibility function on the low
level space but then Omega can be
computed independently in the high level
space and they can be combined so this
decomposition property is really nice
because we never want to work in a
product space
especially as we learn tons of Dynamics
about how the world works we need to we
need to be able to compute
representations in a factorized way
which is going to help us move around uh
in reason
so
the this means that you know when we
compute
um a bunch of uh individual State time
feasibility functions for each goal I
don't know why this little hat is here
but
um
then if we have you know five of these
and we have an aggregate feasibility
function
then we can use this aggregate
feasibility function
to move around from
uh from feature to feature in the low
level World and update all of our
internal and higher level States
and so
this is the object from the previous
slides that that sort of map us around
the world
so you can also do and I won't talk
about this much but you can also you
know do logical tasks where instead of
eating an apple you might want to gather
an Apple so if you if you go obtain an
apple then there could be a bit that
corresponds to having an apple and you
flip that bit to one once you go to the
tree and then you go gather water at the
lake and you flip that bit and then you
go to the key and you uh obtain that key
and that might be a task where you have
to do these three you have to obtain
these three items perhaps because you
wanted to compose this task with
something else you want to you know
bring these items to another agent or
whatever so the point is is that you can
use these factorizations to move around
the world especially when you know
things in the world have a sort of
limited time period in which they are
available
so
um
so yeah I talked about
how we can plan in these high
dimensional State spaces
uh using this factorization
and now
um we get to the question well why
should I
plan to any particular High dimensional
States that's the intrinsic motivation
question you know given that there's an
exponential number of State vectors in a
product space Y is one why is one state
Vector of the world you know in the
far-off distance better than another
so that's where empowerment comes in
empowerment is an intrinsic motivation
metric which sort of represents
controllability so formally empowerment
is a function of a transition operator
it's a it's an intrinsic uh measure of
an intern of a transition operator and
it's and you can also condition it on
the states that an agent is at so it
takes two arguments
it also has a horizon n which we'll talk
about in a second
um so it's formally defined it's the
Shannon Channel capacity between your
actuators or sequences of actions that
you take and the resulting States so the
channel capacity
uh so here you know an open loop
sequence of actions would just be a you
know go up right and up again or up left
and then down
um there's a whole bunch there there are
a lot of possible sequences of actions
so big a here is a random variable for
your sequences of actions and so for a
horizon n you can ask what's how much
information can we transmit from our
actuators to the resulting State at time
Tau so Tau minus uh Tau minus t is our
Horizon uh n which is this parameter on
the empowerment so it's just saying you
know how much what's what's the agent's
capacity to affect the future with uh
certainty or or varying amounts of
certainty
and so the channel capacity is formally
defined as the maximum Mutual
information Givens uh distribution over
these action sequences
um and the mutual information decomposes
into the entropy of the final States
minus the conditional entropy of the
final State random uh random variable
given that you know given the actions
and and your starting state
so
this means that there are two sort of
like
extremes to empowerment
um if PX is a deterministic operator
and so anytime I'm at State X and I
apply an action I get a deter
deterministic output X Prime
then
um the conditional entropy
there there's going to be no uncertainty
over my future States so the entropy is
going to be zero there's no uncertainty
and so that means that the conditional
entropy has to uh cancel out and so
empowerment is really just the maximum
possible entropy given
this distribution and this just reduces
down to the log of the number of
possible reachable States so how much
can I actually reach
in the world
um
and so you know if my Horizon is two we
can see that the empowerment here is
just log of 13. so I get there are 13
states I can get to and I have perfect
control so I can actually realize any of
those 13 states if I want
and the Other Extreme is if like if PX
is action independent meaning that any
sort of state that I'm in I have an
action that maybe there's a the same you
know distribution given that action say
a uniform distribution
[Music]
um then you know my conditional uh
my uh and my conditional entropy given
the actions is just going to be uh the
entropy and so the empowerment has to be
zero because this term is going to
cancel out
um and so there might be a lot of States
you can technically reach because I can
select actions I'm just going to go
random places so pink is all the states
I could possibly reach but I don't have
any control over which state I'm going
to result I'm going to end up in
and so I can't influence my future in
any way
um
even though there are a lot of possible
Futures so empowerment in that extreme
is zero and then there's
um you know an in-between Zone where you
know you take actions and there's a bias
in One Direction or there's different
distributions for each action and so
there might be uncertainty but you can
sort of control how much information you
can sort of control what state that you
want to end up at
okay so what I'm going to Define is a
function valence
um and
it's important to note that you know
there's there's two arguments uh the
states and you can include the time too
and the conditioning side so you have
empowerment uh
and
um so you can define a diff an
empowerment difference so say you start
at uh s and t
and then you
um end up at a future State and time
after you've execute some sequence of
policies so row here
uh appended to the s t is a sequence of
policies and S row and T row are the
resulting States
then you can compute an empowerment
difference
and this will be our valence function
so Q here is our is a function I'll talk
about in in just a second but we can see
that
um
our our jump operator that's moving
around High dimensional space
is defined as this factorization so we
don't have to represent it remember
that's an important part
and so we can sample you know multiple
policies from this or chains of policies
so if I have policy one policy two then
I'm going to have some resulting State R
double Prime X double Prime TF2
um and so Q here can just represent out
the output of chains of policies so you
can imagine you know a tree search of
chains of policies and Q is just
summarizing the final state of those
branches in a research of policies of
chains of policies
all right
so we can use this Q right so notice
that this Q here is in the expectation
over here so uh it's linking our
original state time to the final State
time so it's the empowerment after some
chain of policies
okay so if we have
[Music]
um
uh so say we have a deterministic
operator and this should be a p
um then valence is an empowerment
difference we can have a simple sort of
example here where we have two hikers
that are considering two different plans
and so
if this tree here is like the space of
um you know two possible chains of
policies
then these hikers are just executing you
know one sort of path through this tree
so the um
the hiker on the so they both have the
same empowerment because they're
starting at the same state
and they're both too away from starving
so they if we just consider an
empowerment at the beginning that's a
log of 13.
and if we chain together two uh two
policies here we can advance our
um
internal State space and the agent will
end up down at the lake
and so given that it's at the lake
you'll notice that it's one state away
from uh from dying so that there's
effect an effective range of what it can
uh where it can go so the empower the
final empowerment is log five because
there's five reachable states and we're
assuming determinism to make this easy
so the valence here and this should be
PS uh here but I have t here but the
valence is just log 5 minus log 13 and
that's the difference between the final
and the initial and so that has a
negative valence uh the the hiker the
yellow
Spirit hiker is clearly in a worse
position that he started off at
but we can advance the uh other hiker
with uh Pi G3 to the lake and then Pi G4
to the tree
and updates
his internal States
and we can see that he's three away from
dying so there's a bigger effective
range
um and so there are 25 states that he
can get to and
[Music]
um so log of 25 minus log of 13 is 0.94
which means that uh he is he's better
off than where he started and so clearly
um the second hiker is executing a
better plan
um yet he has more freedom to uh to
engage with other tasks in the world
and so if if we you know searched over
this entire tree of policy chance uh we
could pick the best one uh and then in
this example we're just going to
consider two two of these uh branches
and we'd pick policy IG IG hi G3 Pi G4
all right
so there's also an another interesting
so in in this past example we're just
sort of changing the structure we're
just changing the initial state
um but since empowerment is also a
function of a transition operator
and our operator Bellman equations are
producing transition operators that map
us from State time to State time
then the output of those Bellman
equations the operator Bellman equations
produce transition operators so we can
compute their empowerment
uh so that's that's a deep connection
between development equations and these
intrinsic motivation metrics
so we can do interesting things where we
can say well if the structure of the
world were different then the
feasibility functions that I could
compute in different configurations of
the world would be different so
if
if the honey badger gets a key
and it opens a door in the mountain pass
then it could it could potentially get
through the other side but it's
important to note that this is changing
this the structure of the low-level
State space so p e naught is what we'll
call the the original transition
operator in which we can't go through
the mountain pass
and that means that if we compute State
time feasibility functions kit on this
operator that means PPE here is going
into the development equation
then we're going to produce you know
State time feasibility functions from
those operator Bellman equations that's
this uh object here which means that we
can use it to construct J to move us
around High dimensional space
and so there's a an empowerment for this
J
but then if we get the key and the key
allows us to move through the door it
changes the structure of the world then
that's a different
um that's a different mode of Dynamics
so that means that
all of the supplies on the other side
where we can compute you know
feasibility functions off of a different
mode of Dynamics in which we can move to
the mountain pass and so that means we
can compute things you know
um by compute valence by asking you know
is is this configuration configuration
of the world more conducive to the
agent's core ontology that is the
agent's internal external coupling that
needs to be maintained
um as a as a sort of core object
[Music]
and so we can compute valence just by
changing J the structure of the agent's
abstractions that it moves to go to
um perform tasks in the world so by
Computing empowerment on J we're sort of
computing it in task space we don't have
we don't have to consider all possible
states of the product space we can
narrow it down to
um to operators that move us around task
space that induce Dynamics on you know
key other state spaces that we care
about maintaining such as our
physiological State spaces
okay so here here's a simple example say
uh the honey badger uh starts at the
lake and has some initial
um
empowerment uh just on the low level
operator so that's p
uh five zero
uh there
there's 12 states that can reach but it
also has a task empowerment
um which is actually zero because
there's only one task that it can in
engage at uh in if you don't include
getting the key as a task so
um the circle here is saying that
there's only one one sort of task that
can be done
and so if the agent goes and gets the
key
uh that's going to it's going to uh you
know reduce its physiological States
because it had to travel there
and then it gets the key and it uh
conditions a different mode of Dynamics
so there's different feasibility
functions associated with that mode uh
which I just described on the on the
last slide
then
uh the the door will open and it can
travel back to the lake
and so now that it's at the lake it can
uh go uh eats food on the other side
right so before getting the key uh if it
couldn't get the key if there were no
key then it would just starve because
um well it could drink water and stay
hydrated it couldn't get it couldn't eat
from the apple tree but now it can cycle
back back and forth between the apple
tree and the lake uh for as long as it
wants and so it has a higher empowerment
just on the uh on the low-level State
spaces but also has a higher task
empowerment because there are you know
just over a horizon of three and we're
just Computing uh where we have to
choose a horizon so the empowerment in
task space is eight because there's
eight possible branches in resulting
States from
from where it is and so that's very
useful
um so we can compute the the valence
which is uh 0.5 just in the in the low
level space but also three in the task
space
and another interesting question which
is
um very important is to say well what's
the value of the key and you can compute
this too you can say well given if I
just fix a state Vector that I'm at and
I just alter the state Phi that encodes
the object of a key if I just alter that
state and switch it between having a key
and I event key you can say well this
key is has this much value to the
internal organization the internal
Integrity or controllability of the
agent so it's a sort of agent-centric uh
it uh Judgment of how much something in
the world is valuable and so the key can
be not valuable if it doesn't do
anything in the world that helps the
agent control its core ontology
so this is a way in which you can sort
of bootstrap uh value into the world you
can use it you can use the change in an
agent's internal structure it's coupling
between the internal State spaces and
the external world you can use the
changes in that structure to assign
value to things and it's very useful
okay I think our we're approaching an
hour and so I'll just conclude by saying
um intelligent systems operate in high
dimensional product spaces
often with non-stationary Dynamics this
this introduces a lot of problems
um especially in artificial intelligence
because people normally deal with
structured tasks and non-stationarity by
training you know recurrent neural
networks and things like this which take
which contribute a lot to sample
complexity and what I'm saying is that
you know operator Bellman equations have
this different form which produces
transition operators which helps you
factorize
um your representations for moving
around the world and predicting the
resulting High dimensional State Factor
and these operators are composable they
compose with themselves but they also
compose with higher level structure so
you can remap different transition
structures to them it's very modular and
these are very nice properties that you
that you need
uh if you want to if you don't want to
recompute things and you want to have
sort of modular structure come in and
remap to your representations that
you've already computed
and then so
forward sampling
uh can you still hear me Daniel
okay just checking so forward sampling
is a good way of solving a problems in
high dimensional State spaces without
representing the product space we can't
really solve we can't do dynamic
programming in a huge product space
that's not going to work we can't sample
low-level actions that's not going to
work it's the the tree is too big but we
can uh we can work at the level of
sequences of policies
and we can evaluate empowerment gain to
justify our goal States
and so valence sort of unifies a lot of
distinct drives like there's a different
sort of subfield of RL called
multi-objective
reinforcement learning which says oh
we'll we'll have a bunch of different
reward functions and then we'll have
value functions for each of these reward
functions for like different tasks and
that'll make like a high dimensional
value function Vector space
um and usually in in like
multi-objective RL you have to like pick
a policy that that's in that you know
that's does well
um in that you know value function space
but normally you have to uh you have to
deal with the trade-offs by some waiting
function so what I'm saying here is that
it this allows a because valence is just
one number and it summarizes an entire
sort of control architecture
that you don't have to have introduce
things like waiting functions or
weighting coefficients to say oh this
objective is more important now or this
objective is more important now now
um
so yeah many latent drives is not
necessarily multi-objective it's
multi-dimensional it's multi-goal but it
doesn't have to be multi-objective
um
uh and so yeah with empowerment you
don't have weighted combinations of
empowerment
and
valence uh depends on the structure of
the environment so it's um it's it's not
just some static property of the world
or a static property of an agent it it
incorporates uh agent World coupling
and I thought I'd just
um end with this quote from Terence
Deacon
um who wrote a great book called
incomplete nature which I love and I
read it at the beginning of grad school
and which inspired me a lot and Terence
Deacon wrote a lot about
teleology from a sort of thermodynamic
perspective and it's really compelling
um and I just liked what he had to say
about
teleodynamics the the idea that you know
that an organism could be or Its
Behavior could be organized around
realizing you know something which is
sort of virtual and he says teledynamics
is the dynamical realization of Final
causality in which a given dynamical
organization exists because of the
consequences of its own continuous and
therefore continuance and therefore it
can be described as being
self-generating specifically it is the
emergence of a distinct a distinctive
realm of orthograde dynamics that is
organized around a self-realizing
potential or to be somewhat enigmatic it
is a consequence organized Dynamic that
is that is its own consequence and I
think I think that's relevant to what
I'm doing here because
um I think empowerment sort of on a an
internal
sort of structured ontology allows an
agent to say
there are multiple there there's a huge
space of possible Futures but I can
evaluate you know a state of the world
that's far you know far off in the
distant future
and I can organize all of my behavior
around that because I can say I can give
an explanation for why it benefits uh my
sort of core ontology and so therefore
it makes me
um capable of acting that way in the
future it's a consequence organized
Dynamic that is its own consequence
so um with that I will I just want to
thank the active inference Institute
um and I will take questions and I'm
very interested in you know what active
inference uh theorists think about to
sort of potential for a sort of
integrated view of empowerment because I
think you all have a lot a lot of
experience thinking about generative
models and things of of that nature so
I'd be very curious to know what you
think thank you
excellent thanks a lot
great presentation so this will be a fun
discussion those who are watching live
please feel free to add questions in the
live chat
and you can unshare your screen and
we'll begin
I guess I'll
take an empowering deep breath
and
ask a general question and then I have
some scattered notes that I'll love to
dive into so how did you come to this
area of research what brought you to
control theory modeling and to the
empowerment perspective specifically
um hold on I'm just bringing up the
YouTube stream so I can see comments
right now
um
what brought and
just a general question mute that one
there we go yeah I'll meet that
sounds good thank you
yeah so what brought me to empowerment
I've always been interested in yeah how
you know how how could animals
uh interact in a world in a way that's
so sample efficient especially like you
know knowing that you know animals can
you know like oh like a baby horse can
you know get up and move around and
interact with the world in a sort of
fluid flexible way you know what are the
sort of core representational
capacities that are needed to do that
and I didn't really see anything from
the RL world and this is before I knew
about active inference
um and so that's always been in the back
of my mind and
another big influence
was a guy named nishith srivastava who
wrote an interesting paper about
how you can basically have a sort of
relativistic decision theory that
allowed you to make judgments between
different items without recourse to sort
of hedonic utility Theory maximization
and so he he sort of argued that if
there was something like a latent
acceptability function that you could
you could sort of measure you could sort
of remember a history of item
acceptability and you could remember the
context that you made decisions and then
you could actually just do Bayesian
inference over those memories and you
could explain a lot of interesting
things like preference reversal
phenomena and decision Theory where you
introduced irrelevant Alternatives and
it like changes the fundamental
choice you make and I thought that that
that sort of initiated a lot of thinking
into how could you have
um how could you bring those kinds of
intuitions into sort of embodied
planning like how how could it be that
you have an agent assign value to things
without them being sort of attributed as
sort of static
um sort of static preferences or static
Utilities in the world so I think that
was also a big inspiration
awesome okay and then one short general
question why the honey badger
hey Badger
um yeah my advisor showed me a a YouTube
video of of a honey badger named stoffel
and in my paper reward is not necessary
it's the the opening
um paragraph talks about stoffel and
there's a link to this YouTube video but
stoffel is is is a honey badger in
Australia and
um he he he's at some sort of like
Animal Care Center and he he's really
good at escaping from things so the uh
the caretaker of of
of at this animal sanctuary constantly
has to build you know like elaborate
structures to keep stoffel in so he has
this sort of pen called Badger Alcatraz
and uh stoffel would do interesting
things like you know find objects to
lean against the wall and climb over or
and if you took those away sofa would
pack you know mud into balls and stack
them into like a little pyramid against
the wall to climb up and things like
that so yeah it got me thinking like
what is what is a sort of good General
intrinsic motivation function that isn't
doesn't just work on you know low-level
States but also in a sort of more
conceptual hierarchical space like there
might be objects or mating opportunities
or anything sort of outside Badger
Alcatraz what is a sort of way in which
you could have an agent sort of think in
a sort of abstract way in order to
justify motivate its motivations
so I I encourage the uh the listeners to
to uh look up that video it's
entertaining
it's like this General Escape impulse
yes extended into our open air
context where we also want to maintain
the ability to move and for mobile
creatures
that's quite a good proxy for what we
might want to care about like living
right
all right I'll go to a question in the
chat
from Alex Kiefer
fantastic work maybe a naive question
and I'm sure it's clear in the formalism
which I have only begun to look at but
the idea is that actual agent
environment coupling figures in
Computing empowerment right
if so is there a fully internal proxy
that can be optimized given information
available internally
hmm is there
let's see
is there a fully internal proxy that can
be computed that can be optimized given
info
available
internally in that part of the coupling
does he mean
I I suppose I mean you I suppose you
could compute empowerment just on the
internal State space
um but I don't know I actually I kind of
want to say no just because you do need
to use actions to move around and
influence other state spaces and things
like this
um I don't know how I would
compute yeah just a sort of internal
yeah intrinsic motivation function that
that isn't a part of some coupling to
some broader system
what about the desire to think freely
and to move in cognitive spaces broadly
yeah I agree that's that okay so yeah I
definitely agree if I mean if you have
all of your sort of physiological you
know needs met and there aren't sort of
imposing themselves on you you're sort
of freed up to do other things right
um so yeah I think that
this could work generally into very
abstract spaces maybe even mathematical
spaces
um and
yeah I think that there can be dependent
like higher level dependency structures
in you know abstract thought or
mathematical thoughts or things like
this I mean you think about you know
faulty proofs that that sort of like
destroy an entire field or something
like uh there there's a sort of
dependency structure in which you
the you know if if you're working on
mathematics that assume some proof is
true and it turns out to be false then
you know perhaps that's disempowering
from a sort of abstract
uh perspective I suppose
so that would be yeah
and when they're again you are yeah
good I was just going to say but again
yeah all that mathematics is being done
by you know some system that has to uh
perform computation which takes energy
and stuff like that so it's always
sort of constrained constrained by them
well constrained by some kind of
external internal coupling yeah
many ways to go let's let's swerve
towards active inference and then see if
we can come back to some other areas
um
you mentioned the generative model of
active inference but you
took a different approach there's
different model ontology so just broadly
how would you structurally contrast the
coupling of the agent in the environment
in active inference and in what you've
proposed because the representations
that we see in active inference often
feature the particular partitioning
where a Markov blanket of a Bayesian
graph is intermediating between internal
and external States and then there's a
mapping function between those internal
and external states such that they can
um engage in an Adaptive coupling again
mediated through the blanket which is
interpreted as providing incoming
sensory observations and outgoing
actions so structurally is that
compatible incompatible or some other
secret third thing with what you
proposed
yeah so I would start off by saying that
I think the thing that makes my work
different is that it's the structure of
the you know the latent just sort of
discrete State space it's that structure
that's under consideration and I think
and I think that inactive inference
usually in code
things like homeostatic drives right you
encode them in a generative model right
correct they're encoded as a preference
over sensory observations so that the
entity uh seeks out and selects
ultimately policies that reduce or bound
their surprise about those observations
like I expect and prefer myself to be at
a homeostatic temperature I'm not
surprised when I'm in that range and I'm
going to undergo action so that I find
myself in that range
yeah yeah so I would say that that is a
major difference
um because the
because the state space in my case has
this sort of self-undermining quality
where it's like bad you know starvation
States it's not it's not really a
surprise an expectation of receiving a
particular signal or having a preference
over some state of the world it has a
sort of uh self-undermining quality that
affects your ability to control every
everything else
so I think that I would
yeah I think I would contrast it that
way that's usually the preferences or
the quality of the states are sort of
encoded uh in a generative model in the
active inference setting and here I'm
saying that there's a sort of structural
coupling that's giving rise to these
valence signals
um
you mentioned the key being obtained as
inducing this change in the agent's
ontology
and one that was ultimately reflected by
increasing empowerment hence increase in
valence so how does it come to
understand that this shiny object
unlocks that door
yeah I wish uh yeah I mean I think that
uh throughout my career I will try to
make steps towards like you know
actually
um actually figuring that out because a
lot of this would comes down to Dynamics
learning you know if an agent doesn't
know what a key does right it's not
going to know that it opens a door and
therefore that it can move through the
door and things like this I think there
are a lot of sort of maybe like Dinah
like
algorithms in which you sort of
alternate between learning learning
things about Dynamics or things like
this but that that is a sort of
outstanding question for me is like yeah
how would you take a key and learn
exactly how it's changing the Dynamics
um
but yeah what I am saying is that given
given that you can do that if if you can
do that then you can really
sort of make these value judgments to
things in the world
so I think that's really important too
because like consider money right like
if I find a 20 bill on the ground I'm
just going to pick it up I don't think
I'm doing a fancy computation right um
of of like oh no my my bank account is
twenty dollars greater and so therefore
I'm gonna I have all this new capacity
or things like this I think I think
these sort of preferences for various
objects like a a key or a dollar bill or
things like this can sort of be you know
stored and maybe you know maybe models
with utility Theory who knows
hmm okay
jumping around to some different
questions
I hope I'm accurate in saying you
described empowerment as a Shannon
information theoretic Channel capacity
between the actuators and the
realization of the state
yeah we might be familiar with hearing
uh Shannon Channel capacity in the
context of bandwidth of information
transfer or upload and download for
example but this is kind of an
action-oriented Shannon Channel capacity
so what is it mean to to get an
intuition on that capacity between the
actuators in the state
yeah so it's it's the channel capacity
is the maximum possible Mutual
information between the actions
you choose and the resulting States so
the
Channel capacity is sort of the maximum
information that you can transmit
from your actuators to possible states
of the world it's it's a it's a form of
optionality that says you know I can
affect
this many sort of possible Futures so
yeah it's a sort of intrinsic property
of an agent
and so in a product space this is going
to be affected
by a lot of different state spaces if
they're interacting like physiological
State spaces can you know kill you if
they get too low
so
I think the interesting thing about this
is that it sort of encourages you to
think about cognition in a in this sort
of interrogative way
um because you know you're essentially
trying to figure out you know what what
you can do but there are a lot of you
know different state spaces that are
hindering that information transfer from
you know your actuators to your state
spaces so I think I think it's very
useful because it can sort of
it's it also sort of leads to like
explainable AI right you can sort of
explain your intentions in terms of
concrete State spaces which which have
structure and explanation things like
that
um I think I got off topic from your
your question but
um
anything else on channel Shannon Channel
capacity that I should talk about
um
I think before we Loop it back to
potentially expected free energy
uh you mentioned the
um AI
topic and is there any risk
of an imperative that features its own
empowerment
in terms of an AI being able to then
select action policies that might not be
what anyone else expects or prefers
may not even be concordant with their
own encoded explainable AI priors but
rather something that takes an
unbounding approach
yeah I do think that that is
um a fear I don't I haven't thought that
much about like the alignment questions
so I'd be very interested in in what
like alignment researchers think of this
perspective
um I think that there's a lot of
interesting work to do on sort of
multi-agent empowerment especially with
these sort of abstract uh transition
operators that work on long time scales
um and you know you can see
that house sort of socialization matters
and things like this
um you know if you're you know in a
world with multiple agents
um
do you have to you know do you have to
learn to respect all of the agents you
know empowerments I mean they can also
act against you right
um so yeah I don't know I do think it's
a fear to take seriously
um I don't know how I would do it though
because it's it's an outstanding
research question to me
coming from an ant colony background you
mentioned the socialization and I
immediately thought well let's just say
that the seeds take two or three Nest
mates to carry home
so in order to have one Nest mate
achieve the maximum empowerment they
must also engage in a pro-social
environment because if anyone else even
if their model is like smaller and less
empowered if they just decide not to
play then that individual until it
figures out how to carry the seed Home
Alone
is going to actually be kind of
um Tethered to a social fabric
that helps it actually obtain those
goals so it puts the social imperative
as a screen in front of potentially any
other imperative
just not
um yeah that's a great that's a great
thought
you mentioned the decomposition of
some function I'll let you unpack what
exactly what function was being
decomposed and you you
um you Justified that by saying we never
want to work in the product space
yeah
from a computational complexity
perspective or however makes sense what
are the dangers or what are the scaling
features of that product space and then
what is the decomposition that
facilitates a more tractable form
yeah I'll share my screen again we can
go back to that slide
thank you
let's see
foreign
[Music]
you can see my screen yep and maybe even
a brief summary of what is a Bellman
equation and how did you move from the
standard formalization of bellman
equations into this operator space
sure yeah the standard Bellman equation
I don't know the button for one slide
forward but okay so the standard
dominant equation just says this uh
recursive form
and it just the value of a state that
you're at
the the optimal value of that state is
the maximum it is the maximum value that
you can get by choosing an action that
rewards you
and takes you to a state from which you
can act in the future to get more reward
so the Bellman equation
um can be solved by dynamic programming
um in order to maximize this function V
so it'll it'll it'll result in a policy
that moves you around the world uh in a
way that accumulates a reward that
you'll find in your environment
um so it has this recursive form uh you
can you can sort of unroll it into a
sequence
um and then the operator Bellman
equation has this similar recursive form
where now
you'll notice that there isn't a reward
function there's this availability
function and it returns a number between
zero and one it returns a probability
and so that's significant because it
makes it means that you can maximize the
cumulative feasibility
and so F here is just saying this goal
is available either you achieve the goal
now or you take an action you don't
achieve it now but you've taken an
action in which you'll achieve it in the
future
so that
um it has the same form where you can
sort of think of an availability
function as a reward but it's
maintaining a probabilistic
um form and that probabilistic form is
importance because it's what allows you
to compute the state time feasibility as
a transition operator as an operator
that Maps you from where you are now the
state time you're at now which is XT
to the final State time and goal that
you achieve
so under the policies so it says if I
start at XT and I follow this policy and
I'm choosing actions that move me
through this state space
then I'm eventually going to get to the
goal and I want to know the final State
and time the probability that I uh
achieved this at any given state in time
and so the state time feasibility
function is here as it's expressed is a
transition operator with one action
which is the policy but when we
aggregate it oh bring this up when we
aggregate it into multiple possible
feasibility functions that are centered
around
uh multiple sort of objects in the world
then all of the policies associated with
with each one of those these are goal
condition policies that that are going
to terminate on
achieving the goal of going to one of
these features and and you know getting
the Apple for instance then those pop
each of those policies is an action for
this transition operator so there's five
five possible policies that are going to
take you around the world around the
space so these operator development
equations have this probabilistic form
which retain this probabilistic
structure
and you can sort of compare this with
um I don't know if you're familiar but
there's this concept in RL called the
successor representation
um which is like often a Hot Topic in
you know computational neuroscience and
the successor representation
is sort of talked about like it's this
predictive operator but really what it
represents is expected State occupancies
under a policy and those expected state
occupancies are awaited by the discount
Factor so it's really a for it's really
a successful representation is really a
sort of weighted statistic
and it doesn't map
from like an initial state to the state
of achieving of inducing an event of of
achieving a goal these are
so where successor representations
aren't compositional you can't multiply
two successor representations and get
another successor representation but you
can multiply matrices that represent
feasibility functions because they're
mapping
their their probabilities so of events
so you can you can combine them just by
multiplying you know matrices that
represent you know the state time
feasibility function for a given policy
with another one for a different policy
so that will
um retain a
the form of a probabilistic function and
that's what makes them reusable
composable
Etc
and I think you asked me about the
decomposition
and this decomposition
yeah I might have glossed over this but
the decomposition result is that if you
have if you were to compute a state-time
feasibility function in a product space
okay which has lots of State lots of
States lots of State vectors which are
each States
um then
you know you don't want to do that
because product spaces are very large
and take a lot of you know in memory to
represent the operator uh so if if this
was not PX and this was PS and PS was
the full product space operator that
moves you around this High dimensional
space well you can't really represent
that and you don't really want to but if
you did and you computed a state time
feasibility function in a product space
then you can under certain conditions uh
and I can say what those conditions are
but under certain conditions you can
decompose this into a prediction of all
of the higher level State spaces
computed independently so you evolve the
hunger space separately and you evolve
the their space separately and you
evolve the temperature space separately
you can do all of those computations
locally on those spaces
um and you can combine them with a state
time feasibility function that's only
computed on the low level space so
um so this hierarchical stf of the state
time feasibility function is an
intractable object for for most
reasonable reasonably sized problems but
you can implicitly form it by this
product of these things individually and
so this works when you're when your goal
if for the for the uh hierarchical
state-time feasibility function when you
just have a single goal at arriving at a
particular feature of the world like a
tree
um
that's that's this that's the sort of
can that's one of the conditions in
which this decomposition holds so I
think that that answered your question
about you know the burden of a product
space well you need to uh you need to
overcome it by doing local computations
on individual State spaces in a sort of
network
of interconnected State spaces
that implicitly form a product space but
you you want to compute all of the
representation separately in this
network of State spaces so that you can
sort of move around this High
dimensional State space under successive
policies
and so that's that's what allows you to
handle
forward sampling in in this High
dimensional State space and that's
that's important because I I think
and just to um recall uh the sort of uh
presentation I think was aval a-a-v-e-l
who yes
yeah just to Echo that that sort of
sentiments that
if you're composing if you're creating
new state spaces or you're composing
you're not Computing policies in a fixed
world
um you're composing things together
um that's of course going to expand the
product space implicitly of all the
state vectors of the system and the act
of composing thing or bringing new
information in is expanding the implicit
product space that you are in
and so from an RL standpoint
um it's not so clear you know what a
reward function on that product space is
even supposed to be I don't think that
anyone will
I answered that question but it's also
not clear what you know what a
generative model should look like on
that product space either and I think
given that you know organisms or humans
at least are so skilled at this at this
sort of dialectical process of proposing
theories in you know composing structure
um as hypotheses and in
um in interrogating what that means I
think that they're I think that value
comes from interrogating you know what
it means for the structure of the world
to be a certain way so if I if I learn
new dynamics of the world and I want to
control
Dynamics on some new space it might
affect other state spaces but you know
from a normative perspective it's not
really clear you know when once you
compose something in your and you're
expanding the implicit product space
it's not so clear where any sort of
normative source of normativity should
come from but I think the sort of
flexible human reasoning that we sort of
know humans to engage in I think is in
this sort of regime of composition and
interrogation where you're always sort
of saying oh if the world were this way
then I'm sort of I I then I could see
how this state space affects these other
state spaces in a way that I didn't
anticipate and so I think normativity in
a creative way has to come from
controllability
that that would be my argument
there's a lot
there so if you directions
first to our colleagues in reinforcement
learning RL
the paper is provocative in that it
includes reward is not necessary so
is reward sufficient
and or what is necessary
for what
yeah it's a good question is is reward
sufficient I think
I would argue this you know
I think
that the reward enough hypothesis which
just to remind the some of the viewers
is the hypothesis that reward
maximization
can account for all sort of artificial
and sort of natural intelligence that
all of the sort of features of
intelligence the sort of capabilities
the
structure learning and stuff can all
sort of arise out of some need to
there's some some process of maximizing
reward and
from my standpoint this that's a
frustrating statement because it's
one it doesn't
um
one it doesn't really address
where your preferences for specific
reward functions come from and in the
paper that they will say well we
acknowledge you know that there could be
multiple sources of reward
and but you know the process of deciding
on what you know reward you should
attend to or care about that's I think
is is a deciding what signals you should
care about is an important part of
intelligence itself and I think that
reward is enough hypothesis as a
hypothesis is sort of under constrained
in that whatever that mechanism is to to
that perspective it's going to be
maximizing reward you know under their
Paradigm and so therefore whatever
whatever shapes what that mechanism is
that that you know an agent should
attend to this or an agent should stop
attending to the things that's always
cared about in and attend to some new
signal
I think that that call you know I think
that that forces you to sort of
take the position that you know maybe
there's a meta Source like a meta reward
that tells you that that directs this
process because all sort of attendant
processes of intelligent systems sort of
are underlie the process of reward
maximization and also you know
it the the reward the reward is enough
hypothesis
is not being specific about
it doesn't tell you what necessarily to
compute it just says that if you try to
maximize reward it will you will
you will compute the right
uh representations and so I think that
there's just a lot of like nuts and
bolts about
what it takes to be able to reason in a
flexible human way in what I'm proposing
here with the operator Bellman equations
is to say hey look there's these
reward-free Bowman equations that help
you deal with the complexity of the
world there's no reward in them and you
could make the case well maybe you could
just use these operator development
equations to occupy states that are
rewarding but I would argue that since
the product space the effective product
space that we all live in is so vast
and we reason about it in such a
flexible way I very much doubt that RL
will rise to the challenge of being able
to justify motivations in real time in a
way that humans can and so to get to the
question of you know is it sufficient
my hunch is no I can't like I don't have
a proof of like you know reward is not
sufficient
um but I also think that the information
that a reward function is supposed to
carry about what is good I don't think
that that is that is Noble or computable
on the time scales that we understand
human intelligence to to work at to work
on and so yeah in order to answer your
question about what is necessary I don't
know
what is necessary but I would just sort
of
make the point that I already made of
that I think that we have to get to a
point in which we sort of acknowledge
the problems of product spaces and sort
of reasoning dialectically in a product
space that we can't explicitly represent
uh and so I don't know
I don't know what is necessary but I can
say that it's not necessary for simple
self-preserving agents and that's the
claim of the paper
awesome
all right in our
closing segments
I'd like to take a journey to philosophy
and then connect this back to
potentially
relationships
between the models that you've presented
here and active inference and maybe even
walk
to the edge of that Cliff of the hybrid
model so
Aristotle proposed four causes
material cause what something is made of
the efficient cause which is the source
of change
the formal cause is the essence and the
final cause is the the teleology the end
goal of the object and your
presentations
was Deacon's
analysis of these different forms of
teleology
and
indeed within the model proposed
empowerment was that type of
self-referential teleology
when
juxtaposing with active inference and
specifically the expected free energy
functional which has a lot of analogies
with an operator it's a function of
other functions the expected free energy
functional
is
predicated around helping the agent
select policies that over expected
Futures reduce their uncertainty the
most about which Sensations they receive
and that's what ties active inference
closely with perceptual control theory
that that expected free energy
is ultimately looking at a Divergence
between preferences over observations
and incoming observations so that's kind
of the sense side of the coin it's like
I want to stay in the game to be able to
align observations with my preferences
and I'm wondering if
empowerment is the action side of the
game
you'll be involved with yes repeatedly
sensing yourself to not be starving not
be dying of thirst not be dying of cold
like you'll be in your preference vector
by way of this single value
which is the empowerment whereas active
inference kind of comes from the other
side saying you're going to end up
having a lot of squares to move around
in But first you need to make sure that
you're reducing Divergence between your
preferences and your expected
observations
what do you think about that map or
where would that take these intertwined
models
well I think that there could be like an
interface between the two concepts if we
consider that models of how things work
like composed models of how things work
could induce
particular generative models
that you would want to use in a sort of
active inference setting and that would
be the sort of dual nature between the
two that there's a cross talk between
the proposal of of some kind of
generative model that would be conducive
to the agent
and
if it is then it's a good then it could
be a good State encoding which feeds
back in on you know controllability or
empowerment and things like this so I
mean there's a lot to think about on
this topic
um but I guess I would just put put it
that way that
um that we still need to justify
where
generative models come from uh in new
situations for new theories of how
things work and things like that
you know there could be a dual process
in which
the action side the internal
controllability side is dictating
[Music]
what kinds of generative models that we
that should be considered
very
interesting and the reason I brought up
Aristotle's causes was because active
inference as a process Theory
seems to be describing that efficient
cause
it's just especially with a variational
free energy which is kind of the real
time version of the expected free energy
it's like one step at a time
ball going downhill and so variational
inference is enabling incremental
unfolding optimization again oriented
around reducing that sensory preference
and outcome
it
does everything but specify a final
cause in a sense
one might say that there's a local final
cause within the active inference
generative model which is like to reduce
the Divergence between the preferences
and the observations
but the generative model
also
from the action selection side which is
what makes active inference active
inference it also needs
a final cause
in that
self-referential teledynamic way
and so there could be some very
interesting
architectures where
active inference picks up
where empowerment leads like through a
needle
because it's such a small representation
with valence
and then one other kind of connection or
maybe mapping between them is we've seen
models of valence in active inference
such as the affective inference work
where valence was associated
broadly with whether things are going
better or worse than expected in terms
of statistical uncertainty if you're
reducing your uncertainty more than you
expected things are going better than
expected and vice versa
um so that is a very
variance
oriented
valence Concepts
where broader
uncertainties are associated with
inferior valence and Tighter
positive valence and it's just
interesting that that's kind of like an
orthogonal valence concept
from how much you can actually do that's
the actionable valence would you rather
have a high Precision around not being
able to do anything
or High uncertainty
about being able to do a lot or a huge
amount
and so it almost seems like when we
contrast those two
the direction that dominates is
in the final analysis the ability to
have empowerment not necessarily to just
have tight control over your
observations
yeah
yeah I agree lots lots of interesting
avenues for hybrid theories
well what a very
interesting talk I guess one more
question on the model and then we'll
close which is
the time Horizon
is it an infinite time horizon or
what is the treatment of time and can
time be continuous or is time always
discrete and is it finite or infinite
Horizon
it's uh so the operator Bellman
equations are formalized as a finite
Horizon
I suppose they could be extended to
infinite ryzen and infinite
um or continuous time I suppose that's
possible too
but as as they're formalized now it's
discrete State discrete time finite
Horizon
um
but yeah I mean I think that there is
there's Alternative forms that could be
could be made
[Music]
um
is the was there another question too in
that I can't remember
let us close with your time Horizon
what are your next steps with the
research and how would you imagine an
ecosystem of continuation of the work
yeah I'm I'm interested in getting this
work into
computational Neuroscience
[Music]
um
uh because there's a lot of I think
alternative models that need to be
considered especially given some of the
themes that I've touched on in terms of
justifying what to do in a product space
how do you represent
control in a distributed system Etc
um and so I think that there's a lot a
lot to do there in computational
Neuroscience on the AI side I want to
put this in a world model
I want to uh get good you know Auto
encoders kind of like how I had on on
the first slide where you have a high
dimensional you know agent in a high
dimensional multimodal world how do you
how do you have nice World models and
put this in in something like that so
that's that's the AI future Direction
and I'd like to do both of them so
a lot of work to do
awesome well in closing I'm just going
to read some of the more statement like
comments from the live chat just so that
they're included in the active inference
Journal so Dave Douglas wrote
with regards to Deacon's consequence
Galileo may have gotten in trouble less
from insisting on a heliocentric
Universe than from insisting that
purpose value and meaning
be banished from science as connecting
explanatory principles
the Galileo tolerated remaining
connecting principle causation may have
reached the limits of its explanatory
power sometime between Newtons and four
years day
where all respectable principles of
explanation must ultimately rest on
invocation of either rigid rods or on
elastic bands
the Galilean program of Sola casa
attained its absurdity in karnap's
insistence that meaning value
counterfactuals must be judged as
strictly and literally as meaningless
have we passed the point when the
Galilean program must be simply
abandoned and meaning value and purpose
must be restored to science as
irreducible explanatory principles
alongside causation
I find the mysticisms of both boom and
Heisenberg's Quantum completeness and of
Pauli and Young's synchronicity to just
be too fluffy to be very useful in a
word it has become a tradition of
science as funded
to insist that causation and causation
alone must bound our Enterprise this is
a tradition of men not a feature of
Ultimate Reality meaning and value also
have their place Not reducible to cause
I like it yeah
excellent well Thomas thank you again
for joining you're always welcome back
and really looking forward to seeing how
this all continues
me too and thanks again for having me
I've been very impressed with how much
work you do for the Discord and uh it's
it's a it's a great Community I can
everyone's very very nice and
enthusiastic so I was excited to see it
I just sort of randomly stumbled across
it so I'm glad uh I'm glad I introduced
myself to to the Discord so thank you
excellent all right till next time thank
you great thank you